[Music]
Welcome back to Golden Rule Radio, your
weekly recap of the precious metals
markets and the news that moves those
markets. This week, we'll start as
always with a brief recap of the week.
And we're also going to get into the
technical analysis on a more detailed
level as well as the fundamental recap
as to what has transpired this week and
what we see transpiring in the future
weeks that will impact the gold price.
Yeah, Tori, gold down about 5% from our
recording last week to 3170. A little
under 3,200 an ounce coming off the
significant high scraping 3500 here a
couple weeks ago. So, that puts us down
about 7% since the most recent high and
9% since that almost $3,500 all-time
high back in April. Sticking within some
trading ranges that we're going to take
a closer look at here in a few minutes.
Silver's actually relatively stable and
been sitting around $32 an ounce now
with about a month-long trading range up
and down about 3%. And despite not
entirely following gold up and down,
silver is still looking pretty healthy.
We always like to take a look at
platinum versus palladium. A couple
industrial sister precious metals.
Platinum stable in the 960s. Not really
up or down this past week. Just treading
water there in the mid 900s, but
arguably inching its way up with a
little bit of a short-term declining
trend. and we're sitting at the top end
of that. Palladium relatively similar,
although technically down about 2%, it's
also been in a nice long-term trading
range and sitting just below platinum
this week at
$950. Palladium's long-term trading
range is now at about 16 months of some
pretty significant movement up and down
between about $,50 and 850. So, we're
still parked right in the middle of
that. Uh quick glance at the paper
markets. The S&P back up a little bit
more this week about 4% sitting just
under
5900. We're coming into some important
resistance area just below the previous
high. So I do think the stock market
after that 20 plus% decline really
deserves some eyes here over the next
couple of weeks to see if we can push
back up towards those previous highs.
And everything revolves around the US
dollar, Tori. And the US dollar while up
about half a percent, currently sitting
at
101.5, that sub 100 number we saw back
in April, that breaks a three-year floor
that we talked about on our show a
couple weeks ago. And although we have
pushed back up in the dollar slightly, I
don't know, Tori, I think arguably the
dollar continues down. So, where do we
want to start this week with some deeper
look at a couple different market
charts? Well, let's do a deeper dive on
the dollar because I think it'll help
lend a little bit of color to the
conversation as we dive deeper into the
metals. That dollar conversation to me
is very, very intriguing. Two weeks ago,
you had a great image on that inverse
correlation between the dollar and the
gold price, just mirror images of each
other. Is there an expected continued
rally here? I'll preface it by saying
President Trump wants a weaker dollar.
And so you make that comment and that's
justifiable. What we may see here is a
continuation of a little bit of a pop.
And we'll get into some of the
fundamental reasons for that later, but
let's do a little bit deeper dive on the
dollar. Yeah. Well, you want a weaker
dollar, but you want a weaker dollar
alongside lower interest rates. What you
don't want is higher interest rates and
a weaker dollar. I don't know if that
necessarily helps anybody. we've got to
avoid inflation. At the same time,
they've got this tight rope that they're
walking of trying to improve our
exporting and employment environment, if
you will, and yet not driving inflation
significantly higher. Right? And part of
the reason I think that gold has come
down and the dollar has gone up is going
back to last week's failure of a rate
cut and next month's expected failure by
the Federal Reserve to cut rates. Even
though again yesterday, President Trump
came out saying that Chairman Powell is
too late to react and that he should be
cutting rates already because again
that's stimulative. But do we want to
stimulate inflation? Absolutely not.
We'll get into some of that later too
because the CPI numbers are actually
showing the opposite. That's pretty
important news on where core CPI is
gone. But before we leave the dollar, I
do think it's important to mention David
Melaney, president of our company and
host of the Melaney weekly commentary
podcast, which we encourage everybody to
listen to as well, brought up a good
point here recently. Maybe this is just
the eye of the hurricane, but April
actually, despite all the tariff
concerns and price movements and
everything, which leads into that CPI
conversation, April we had a surplus. If
I'm not mistaken, according to Dave and
some research he did, I think it was the
first Fed surplus for a month since
2001, which Bush inherited from Clinton.
So, we are looking at at least a one
month Fed surplus. Now, a lot of that is
coming on the heels of things like some
delayed tax payments coming out of
California and the likes that boosted
some numbers in April. I don't know yet
if this is a new trend to come. I'm sure
we would all love to see that or if this
is just maybe a port in the storm as
we're seeing some massive changes take
place right now with the additional
tariff boost as well as some other
one-off indicators. So, we'll have to
see how this plays out, but ultimately
higher interest rates without the
Federal Reserve playing ball with Trump
and him continuing to push for a weaker
dollar policy, which would include
lowering interest rates, which certainly
is his hope. What concerns me is the
fact that we're not seeing lowering
interest rates, but we are seeing pretty
much all of the benefit gained from
those interest rates in the dollar
valuation globally practically gone at
this point with the dollar pushing back
below 100 here recently and probably
continuing down. Yeah, even though in
the short term this trend may continue
once we've headed north of that 100 mark
again. You kind of drew a really
beautiful floor in an image a few weeks
ago on the US dollar index chart and
that long-term support once was broken
through became a point of resistance and
it didn't take too long to break north
of the 100 mark. So now it wouldn't
surprise me a bit to see the dollar even
go flirt with 102 103 just in the short
term. It goes against the intermediate
and long-term objectives of this
administration. So the long-term picture
again is for a weaker dollar and weaker
dollar equals higher gold prices in the
long run. But be prepared for a little
bit of a pop. So let's dive a little bit
more deeply now into gold. And what do
you see as support levels to the
downside because we're in a correction
or a pullback here if you will? What are
some target figures for you, Miles?
We're coming off pretty significant run
in the physical precious metals, namely
gold. I don't even know if I should say
physical metals because silver did fine,
platinum and palladium did nothing and
gold has been gang busters for the last
month or so. Tori, one of the big topics
that we've been trying to remind our
listeners of and trying to encourage
people to look at it through this lens,
this has been a top-down market push
into gold. So, you're looking at a
relatively gradual downtrend over the
course of April in gold. If you're
looking at the price of gold here,
you're seeing us putting in a top at
around
3500 and then some stair steps downwards
that have been relatively gradual. I've
always argued that reversals happen
quickly. Continuations take extended
breaks. This is a vacation from a what
13 14month push. How long has gold
pretty much been going up non-stop now?
Over a year. It's beautiful. other than
the post election little breather that
it took to close 2024. Coming down off
of the 3500 high, we've stairstepped
down to it, but it is actually
significant that we're now looking at
sub 3,200. So, gold's off about 300
bucks. If you look at just the last push
in the gold price which started back in
January around 2650
2700 and stepped all the way up to
3500 we're sitting at our first major
correction on the short term just this
final last push up in gold. our first
major correction, the 618 Fibonacci
correction sitting right at or just
below 3,200. And then coupled with that,
if we look at the longerterm chart of
this entire move, we're finally seeing
our first longerterm Fibonacci
correction, the 318, which is exactly
what it sounds like. 618, that's about
61% retracement. Three steps forward,
two steps back. the 382 that's about a
third. So we've taken three steps
forward in the long term and we have
finally taken a real step back. Tori,
believe it or not, for the first time in
over a year, we've had an actual
correction. I cannot believe it. And
from my perspective, one of the biggest
things about actual corrections is they
convince us that the market is still
relatively healthy. So this is not the
big breakout move that big manic crazy
say
post208 market crash rise in gold quite
yet. We still don't have that third
phase that final phase push in gold
taking place yet. This is just normal
trading. An analyst, Tori, that I know
you and I both like to read, Christopher
Muan over at the Technical Traders, put
out a great video a couple weeks ago
comparing the current gold market to the
2008 market crash that I know you've
seen because you shared it with me. Oh,
it's just wonderful. And it really goes
objectively pointing to what we all
sense subjectively. Boy, it feels like
we're in this replay of March and April
of 2008 prior to the fall crash, if you
will, where the financial crisis really
gathered momentum. And to me, these
charts that he shows, we'll just put up
the image of a freeze frame of Chris's
imagery here. Really powerful because
you would expect there to be a dollar
rally. You would expect there to
ultimately be a further wash out in the
equities markets. They've shown
themselves to be topheavy, overbought.
There's still a lot of speculation in
the markets. People haven't grasped the
reality. Just because this tariff
agreement with China has been reached
does not mean that the stock market is
not still overbought. It does not mean
that we don't need a wash out. It
doesn't mean that there's not still some
pain to come. But the way that he
overlays these image are really to me
it's a very powerful testament to his
skills but also what we are sensing just
post Bear Sterns in March of 2008. Yeah.
Because our argument that price is
something that we like to talk about
because it gets people's attention short
term. But I feel like one of the things
to you and I have always tried to do is
encourage people to look at things
through fundamental concepts. the idea
that you have a major market like gold,
big money has been buying gold. Here
over at one of our own weekly articles
that we put out, Morgan Lewis writes
hard asset insights. Here in last week's
piece, he's discussing the relationship
between the increased gold buying by
global central banks over the last 10
years and the price of gold. In fact,
it's kind of fascinating that it's not
been the investor, but it's been the
nations that have been causing this push
up in the price of gold. And Vermuan
over at Technical Traders argues that as
well. Like you just mentioned, we're
looking at a gold market right now that
is not the 2009 2010 reaction to the
stock market crash. That's right.
Because the thing that causes people to
react hasn't happened yet. And I think
the retail or individual investor,
whatever you want to call us, the little
guy, not JP Morgan buying up 100 ounce
gold bars to back ETFs, not Goldman
Sachs, not the Bank of China, not the US
for Pete's sake, buying gold for the
first time in who knows how many
decades. But the individual investors
like you and me getting into the
precious metals markets, our involvement
is almost always dictated by an
emotional reaction to something. In
2008, as Vermuan points out, it was a
stock market crash. Money goes first
into cash cuz that's the first fire,
sell everything, and then it starts
looking for alternatives to better
protect itself. And that's when you see
the real move in gold. There are still
phenomenal opportunities in the precious
metals markets in the types of products
that the US government doesn't care
about. 100 ounce gold bars probably not
what I'm interested in buying, but there
are deals in the metals markets right
now in certain types of products that
when the retail investor gets involved,
those things dry up pretty quickly.
Yeah. Even gold American Eagles, a
standard go-to here domestically. Hardly
a price difference between that and a
Canadian maple leaf or a gold bar. So
that's not normal. There is an emotional
reaction going on with the gold price
right now. It's just coming from the
central bank sector with the amount of
debt that the US has pumped into the
system. They have to respond. And this
has been going on since 2008. So talk
about overlaying some charts. There's a
beautiful overlay here as Morgan points
out. Central bank gold buying versus the
gold price chart. Oh yeah. And of course
they're going to do that. the US policy
makers dramatically accelerating our own
dire fiscal deterioration is going to
cause these other countries to respond
because it weaponizes the dollar. We've
had currency wars. Even the response
with Russia really kind of open
Pandora's box and these countries want
alternatives to the US dollar, something
that can't be weaponized. And Trump has
again telegraphed a clear intention to
weaken the US dollar. So, not
surprisingly, the global central bank
gold buying has accelerated to these
record levels. And this pullback is
beautiful. But I'll tell you what, I
don't expect there to be major
pullbacks. We're not going all the way
down past the 618 in my opinion because
the central banks again continue to put
a floor every time we've seen a
correction the last 5 years. China
leading the charge in that regard. So
concrete evidence there of what's really
driving it because you're right, it's
not the retail investor. It's not the
western investor. It's not the coin
buyer. It's not me and you with IAS. It
is central banks. And we'll see if that
continues. And for those wondering, when
Tori mentioned the 618 right there, he's
talking about this final market push
dating back to the beginning of 2025
when we really broke out following the
little break we got in November post
election. But that's gold just at 3,000.
While it feels like a relatively deep
decline, we're still talking about gold
after a correction up a thousand bucks
in slightly over a year, maybe a year
and a half by the time we get down
there. And you know what's crazy, Tori,
is with these inflationary concerns, as
we're starting to get a little traction
economically and our White House
continues to dance through the
victories. If we see a return to lower
interest rates and increased inflation,
there's a concern that people have right
now that Dave Mulaney, Kevin Oric on the
commentary have been talking about here,
the concept of dollar and gold recycling
and just the sheer volume of currency
that's out there internationally that if
threatened may move deeper into gold.
The IMF has already shown us that we're
looking at some of the highest gold
holdings as a percentage by global
central banks up over 20% now. Hasn't
been this high since the mid1 1990s. And
JP Morgan just had an article come out
saying that if half of 1% of the 26 27
trillion US dollars in assets held
outside of the US by foreign investors.
If 1 half of 1% of that went into
something like physical metals, you're
looking at gold well over $6,000 an
ounce just doubling in the price just
from that. Yeah, that's unbelievable.
And I think that you will see a
continuation in that regard of the gold
to silver ratio staying high. Remember,
gold is acting like the money metal that
it is. Silver is far more of a
commodity. And Hedgei, the
riskmanagement firm, and their analysts
have a risk range where they're saying,
"Look, this is the range we expect gold
to trade in in the short term." That
range right now is
3,201 to the downside, 3,431 to the
upside. That's a wide range, $230, but
we've broken through that downside, but
they remain bullish. So, in a bull
market, you take these opportunities to
add to your ounces. The problem that
we're facing is that the gold to silver
ratio is so high. We're still 98 to1
today. So, with all of this volatility,
gold has dropped proportionally a little
bit more than silver has. Silver is
still up more than 12% in 2025. So,
still doing very well, but about half as
well as gold. but we'll take it. But
that ratio being so wide, even though
we're in a bull market in gold and
silver is doing well, it's hard not to
position on the silver side. From a
chart perspective, silver's been hard
stuck in this range for a long time. And
I think that's perfectly fine. Just
because gold has done extremely well
doesn't mean silver hasn't also done
well enough. Look at it this way. JP
Morgan is right. And let's say silver
does terribly compared to gold. you
know, it stays at like a 100 to one
price ratio with gold being a hundred
times the price of silver. That's still
silver at 60 bucks an ounce and it
hasn't even made its move yet. So, my
argument about silver has always been
silver is the poor man's gold and silver
is the thing that we turn to when gold
reaches a price that's just unobtainable
from most people that want it. I don't
know what that price is, but the higher
gold gets, the higher silver will end up
getting because things always revert
back to their means. And the mean on
silver is a heck of a lot higher
compared to gold than where it's at now.
100 to one gold to silver. That's not
sustainable and it ain't going to last
here forever. So yeah, silver will play
catch-up eventually. The trick is just
not caring when it happens. Well, and
remember, even with gold's retracement
here to just under 3,200, by buying
silver today and capitalizing on a ratio
trade in the future, it's like buying
gold at 2600. So, if we do see in that
intermediate term chart where we really
do have a significant pullback to sub
3,000 and we start getting closer, maybe
even to the 200 day moving average,
that's where you're going to get it
anyway. If you buy silver today, let
that ratio correct and you can guarantee
yourself that you're buying gold at
$2,600 an ounce by buying silver today.
And that's why I'm saying that's the
hard thing because this is a monetary
environment. This is a gold as money
type of dynamic that we're witnessing.
And that's what central banks focus on.
Their job is currency. Gold is a
currency. Silver is technically a
hybrid, but really it's not a currency.
And so that to me is what drives it.
Now, as we look at some of the
underlying fundamentals, it's driven
gold. One has been market uncertainty
driven by the tariffs. Well, now we have
a pause. So, Trump has given us a 90-day
halt on some sectors for those tariffs
in regards to negotiations with just
China, which was the big one. It was the
big one. That's what the whole tariff
thing has been centered about. Anyway,
so this is the big one and the target
that this was all predicated on. Well,
it's $500 billion a year in deficit. It
is the big one. And there are a bunch of
smaller ones, but significant. And it
had a dramatic effect on the Chinese
economy. Yes, it was having an effect on
ours. It was having an effect on the
stock markets, which really aren't an
indication of economic health, but they
are an indication of market sentiment or
investor sentiment, if you will. And the
bond market gets twitchy, which nobody
wants. Bonds really set the interest
rate. So nobody wants there to be a bond
market collapse or a loss of confidence
in certainly foreign held government
debt for the US. But all that being
said, you should expect gold to come
down on a little bit of an easing of the
tension and a little bit of clarity on
this topic of uncertainty with the
tariffs. But it's more than that.
Everybody has been doomsaying that the
sky is falling. But Trumpageddon has not
happened yet. In fact, the CPI has
actually come in better and lower than
expected, which you should also expect
gold to pull back on. It's a couple
pieces of potentially positive news. The
end goal would be nobody has any tariffs
on anybody. It's just somebody had to be
willing to bring the other gun to the
gunfight, which Trump was willing to do
with the tariff discussion. So, the fact
that we're getting these sitdowns, I
think, is a positive step in the right
direction. His recent hour-long sitdown
conversation regarding the American
pharmaceutical industry has me wondering
what Bernie Sanders has to say about
him.
There's another front of this war. Yeah,
there's another fist fight on this war
is just the rampant price gouging of the
American public on various things led
out by a very complicated insurance
industry in our US. You got to remember
that he likes to fire cannon shots
across the bow. Sure. No harm, just a
strong message. And I think that's what
we've seen especially this week. And to
me, it has been effective on the tariff
front, but also on the geopolitical
front. We've got Russia and Ukraine
agreeably settling down a little bit
here. You've got Iran who's had a shot
across the bow. You've got the Houthis
in Yemen that have received their
warning shot and have tried to mellow
things out a little bit. You've got this
big Saudi Arabian deal that he has come
to terms with a defense spending one
that's income for the US and
economically stimulating, but it's from
a regional standpoint. It it just puts
our boots more firmly on the ground
there. It's huge. And that's a good
thing. Yes. I mean, so geopolitically
and even Syria, you're looking at him
working with Erdogan. To me, nobody's
talking much about India and Pakistan.
We do a lot of trade with them. I'm not
too worried about that. This is like a
Hamas and Israel repeat cycle that
hopefully doesn't blow up into much
more. But he's saying things like with
the drug companies, he said if
necessary, we'll investigate the drug
companies. Well, that's going to cause
uncertainty in that market, but it'll
scare them straight, too. He's trying to
get prices under control. So, it's
listen to what he says and then watch
what he does and what is a real threat
versus just kind of a red herring. And
he's the master of red herrings in my
opinion. But some of this is absolutely
real. There are some non-negotiables
that we're witnessing. And it will
affect the gold price with every
success. If you have fear settle, if you
have geopolitical tensions reduced, if
you have economic numbers like the CPI
and the good news on the US budget
surplus rising to 258 billion in April.
I mean, even the labor market, the labor
department admitted that hundreds of
thousands of Biden jobs were fake. So,
we're getting some real numbers coming
through, some transparency, and the fact
that China ignored US trade policy
because they considered Biden to be
weak. That's actually a positive. It
means that they're taking Trump
seriously. So, all of these can have
short-term beneficial effect and a
lowering of the gold price. But
ultimately, it's this big, beautiful
bill that's escalating in Congress. Yes,
they're trying to tighten their belt.
But Miles, it's just going to increase
the debt. It's going to increase the
debt ceiling by 4 trillion. We're
already looking at $ 38 trillion, soon
to be 40 by this time next year. How do
we rein that in? No matter how tight you
get that belt, it still seems as if the
outflow is greater. Tori, I think that's
the question because there's short-term
pros and cons and there's there's some
long-term pros and cons. And sometimes
you can't redirect a ship with just a
paddle. So, we'll have to see if some of
these recent actions can help saveave
off some of the potential concerns that
we've been building for the last two
decades. So, I think that's going to do
it this week for Golden Rule Radio.
Please swing by our website if you'd
like some more information. You can find
us at
mlaney.com. We're also on Twitter at a
gold and Facebook at mlaney financial.
If you'd like to discuss your personal
portfolio with one of the adviserss here
at Melaney Precious Metals, you call
18005259556.